Alexander Dean

alexanderjdean.com

Introduction

I'm a software engineer with experience building and deploying large-scale distributed machine learning systems, particularly in the context of preventing credit card fraud. I'm a curious, driven, and collaborative person with strong engineering skills, and I'm passionate about building technology for good. GitHub: alexanderidean.

EDUCATION

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Bachelor of Science, Mathematics and Computer Science

Champaign, IL

December 2021

Email: alex@alexanderjdean.com

Mobile: +1 (312) 298-9551

EXPERIENCE

Capital One

Chicago, IL

Senior Associate Software Engineer (as of July 2023)

Feb 2022 - Present

- Last Performance Rating: Above Strong (top 10-15%)
- **Blob Storage**: Transitioned fraud detection model from Amazon EMR to ETL-style workflows on Kubeflow, storing intermittent results in Amazon S3 as Parquet files; This sped up batch execution of model by 50%.
- Model Training & Serving: Led effort to create two Kubeflow pipelines for fraud model: A build & train and batch execution pipeline. These pipelines enabled model serving, saving half million dollars in 2022 in fraud costs.
- Hadoop Distributed File System: Utilized Spark on Kubernetes clusters to perform MapReduce processing on millions of merchants by ZIP, allowing for model serving on detected geographic fraud rings.
- Publish/Subscribe: Built Kafka-based publishing service in collaboration with senior engineers, used for streaming fraudulent credit card merchants upon model prediction once a week to fraud investigators.
- Microservice Architecture: Took ownership of thorough integration testing (90%+) of API layers in Payments microservice, a large-scale heavy traffic service for call agents helping customers with payments-related tasks.
- Cross Team Collaboration: Assisted multiple microservice teams with integration tests and code quality; Gave multiple presentations to large audiences on thorough integration testing and code dashboards using SonarQube.
- Monitoring & Alerting: Used Splunk and thorough logging to triage incidents, fix high-priority bugs, investigate alerts, test releases, and ensure the continued high availability and low latency use of Payments microservice.
- Mentorship: Served on multiple inclusion, belonging, and learning committees; Led events to encourage inclusion and learning, including Women in Tech advice panels, project demo days, and potluck dinners.

Capital One Chicago, IL

Software Engineer Intern

Feb 2021 - Aug 2021

- **API Development**: Built two new APIs retrieving a customer's credit card agreement version and information, allowing for real-time access to account information instead of previous hours-long batch solution.
- Serverless: Implemented serverless solution for new credit card version and info APIs using AWS Lambda, leading to 98% decrease in monthly costs for cloud computing services relative to previous solution.
- Databases: Reduced size of AWS RDS data instance by removing data retrieval batch job, migrating entries to Amazon DynamoDB, and reducing engine cost of AWS RDS component.

Zengines Chicago, IL

Software Engineer Intern

Sep 2021 - Dec 2021

- Data Generation: Built data generation tool using Python providing realistic sample fake table data given a table schema; This tool is used to test data conversion between two distributed systems.
- Data Augmentation: Used scikit-learn and WordsAPI to expand capital markets dataset by 40%, allowing for evaluation of NLP-based context extractor matching between source and target systems.

PROJECTS

- Documentation & Test Generation: NPM package allowing for conversion of JavaScript projects to TypeScript, with automated documentation & testing generation using the GPT 3.5 API; GitHub page: type-scriptor.
- Automated Satire: Fully-automated satirical news site monitoring recent events and generating Onion-style headlines; Deployed on Google Cloud with Firebase database, React frontend, Node backend. GitHub page: chicagomoontimes.

Programming Skills

• Languages: Python, TypeScript, C++, Go, Java Technologies: AWS, Hadoop, React, Kafka, Kubernetes